Guide to the Mortimer Borne Drypoints 1927–1949 PR 228
New-York Historical Society
Mortimer Borne drypoints
1927–1949
New-York Historical Society
Borne, Mortimer
PR 228
82 item(s) in 1 box.
Drypoints by Polish-born artist Mortimer Borne (1902–1987) depicting Manhattan streets, skylines, harbors, churches, parks (especially Central Park), and elevated trains. Includes views of Brooklyn, Sheepshead Bay, Coney Island, Spuyten Duyvil, and the 1939–1940 World's Fair Grounds at night.
Arrangement
Prints are organized alphabetically by titles supplied by the artist. Titles have been transcribed from each print.
Biographical note
Printmaker, painter, sculptor, and educator Mortimer Borne was born in Rypin, Poland, on December 21, 1902. In 1916 he immigrated to the United States with his parents. He studied at the National Academy of Design, the Art Students League, the Beaux-Art Institute of Design, and with Charles Webster Hawthorne, founder of the Cape Cod School of Art. He taught at the New School for Social Research in New York City from 1945 to 1967.
As a teenager in Poland, Mortimer Borne won a national school competition with a sculptured head of Peter the Great. His printmaking career started in the mid-1920s with a group of drypoint etchings of New York City, and in 1930 his work was recognized by Frederick Keppel & Co., who began representing him. Mortimer Borne's work is in the permanent collections of many museums, but his largest holding is at the Metropolitan Museum of Art.
[Adapted from information formerly posted on the Old Print Shop website: https://web.archive.org/web/20030415162849/http://www.oldprintshop.com/artists/borne.html]
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Noel J. Blackman in 1979.
Related Materials
Other works by Mortimer Borne are found in the James Boyd Collection of New York City Etchings, PR-7.
Scope and Contents
The 82 drypoints by Mortimer Borne in this collection were created between 1927 and 1949. The images, many of them colored, primarily depict Manhattan streets, skylines, harbors, churches, parks (especially Central Park), and elevated trains; several of these are night scenes. There are also views of Brooklyn, Sheepshead Bay, Coney Island, Spuyten Duyvil, and Manhattan as seen from Weehawken, New Jersey, and from the George Washington Bridge. A 1940 etching depicts the World's Fair Grounds at night.
Drypoints (prints); Etchings (prints); Skylines.; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York -- Pictorial works.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Central Park (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Coney Island (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Spuyten Duyvil (New York, N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.) [111] -- Pictorial works.
- Mortimer Borne drypoints, 1927–1949
  - The Ant Hill, Central Park, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - At the Beach—Coney Island 655, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - Automat Vertical, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Bathers—Coney Island, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Beach—Coney Island, 1943 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boathouse—Hudson, 1927 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Boats—Sheepshead Bay, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Broadway from the Trans Lux Building, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bronx Street, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Café, 1933 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carousel—Coney Island, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Central Synagogue—Lexington at 55th St., 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chinatown (Doyers St.—before the fire), 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chinatown, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Church at 79th and Broadway, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - Church of the Holy Trinity (Brooklyn Heights), 1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  - City Hall Park with Civic Virtue, 1936 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Coal Barges at Dusk—Sheepshead Bay, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Coal Yards, Brooklyn, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Columbus Circle—Erection of Skyscraper, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  - Columbus Circle, 1938 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Columbus Circle with Sunkist Billboard, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Construction of West Side Highway, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Demolition of 6th Avenue "El" at 14th St., 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dyckman House, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - E. Fulton Street "El", 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - East 86th St., 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eastside Pushcart at Night, 1927 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  - "El" at 23rd St. & 32nd Av., 1927 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - "El" Lines from Roof on E. Broadway, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - Emanuel from Central Park (Temple with Pine), undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Fireboat (Foot of Fulton St., Brooklyn), 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  - The Fisherman's Line—Sheepshead Bay, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Forest Hills Park, 1933 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Forest Hills Park with Rider, 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fulton St. "El" with Beecher Monument, Brooklyn, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  - Happy Holiday (R & M Borne), 1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Henry Street, Brooklyn Heights, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hicks Street, Brooklyn Heights, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hicks Street, South Brooklyn, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hooverville on Hudson, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Houseboat on the Hudson, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Kew Gardens Landscape, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Little Bridle—Central Park, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  - Long Island Landscape, 1938 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Louis Eilshemius from Life, 1933 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lower Manhattan Skyline from Fulton Street, Brooklyn, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Lower Manhattan Skyline, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
  - Marginal St., 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - May Day—Union Square, 1933 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Museum of Natural History—Indian Hall, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Museum of Natural History—Indian Room #2 with figures, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
  - Negro Preacher, Turpentine Play, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Picnic Grounds—Central Park, 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Plaza Towers from Central Park, 1933 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Plaza Towers, 1930 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ponies—Central Park, 1929 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pretzel Stand Under the "El", 1929 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rainy Night—79th (between Broadway and Columbus), 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Restless Night, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15)
  - Revolving Bridge, New York, East River, 1949 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Riverside Drive, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Skaters, Central Park, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Skaters, Central Park (looking West), 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Skaters, Central Park (with skyline), 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 16)
  - Snow Clearing—Brooklyn Heights, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Station—Inwood (Spuyten Duyvil), 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stock Exchange, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Stone Street—Sunday, 1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17)
  - Temple Emanuel from Central Park, 1931 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Times Square, 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Trinity Church from Treasury, 1947 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Tugboats—Wall Street, 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
  - Union Square from the West, 1929 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Union Square, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Union Square, Panoramic View, 1932 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - Verdi Square Line—72 St. between Broadway and Seventh Av., 1939 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 19)
  - View of Manhattan from G.W. Bridge, 1941 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - View of New York from Weehawken, 1929 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - West 42nd St., 1937 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - West Street at 10th Street, 1934 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)
  - World's Fair Grounds—Night, 1940 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 20)